Guide to the Carlton Sheffield John Steinbeck collection, 1933-1984
Department of Special Collections
Carlton Sheffield's John Steinbeck collection,
1933-1984
Special Collections M0824
Sheffield, Carlton.
.75 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of Carlton Sheffield, 1984.
Biography
Carlton Sheffield was a friend and Stanford roommate of the late author, John Steinbeck. He continued his friendship with Steinbeck after their college years and throughout his writing career through correspondence with Steinbeck and his wife. Sheffield also amassed a collection of clippings, fliers, and articles both about and by Steinbeck, which constitutes the source of this collection.
Sheffield also interacted with and collected information about several foundations and organizations concerning Steinbeck. Most notable in this collection are the Steinbeck Library in Salinas and the Steinbeck Festival, the John Steinbeck Society of America, and the Steinbeck Center Foundation, of which Sheffield was an Honorary Director.
Scope and Content
Included in the collection are carbon copies of Sheffield's correspondence with John and Elaine Steinbeck through the years 1944-1971. There are also copies of Sheffield's correspondence with Peter Lisca, another friend of Steinbeck. The clippings Sheffield collected are also included, covering Steinbeck's books, articles, Nobel Prize, exchanges with Communist writers, tour in Vietnam, and death. Clippings concerning several biographies of Steinbeck and a few related topics (i.e. Steinbeck Country and Cannery Row, and the "Oakies") are also included. Additionally, Sheffield collected clippings of almost any mention of Steinbeck in the newspaper, which we have arranged by date.
The collection also contains a typed carbon manuscript, "The Man in the Shining Silk Hat," by Carol Steinbeck, ca. 1933.
Access Terms
Lisca, Peter.; Sheffield, Carlton.; Steinbeck, Carol.; Steinbeck, John, 1902-1968.; American literature--20th century.
Container List
- Series I: Sheffield's Correspondence, 1945 - 1971
  - Correspondence from Sheffield to Steinbeck (1945-59) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence from Sheffield to Mr. and Mrs. Steinbeck (1961-68) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence from Sheffield to Elaine Steinbeck (1968-71) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence between Sheffield and Peter Lisca (1959) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "The Man in the Shiny Silk Hat": carbon typescript, by Carol Steinbeck (1933) (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series II: Steinbeck's works (clippings)
  - Pastures of Heaven (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Flight (Box 1, Folder 7)
    (clippings and commemorative edition publishing info.)
  - Tortilla Flat (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Burning Bright" (play) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Viva Zapata" (film directed by Eliza Kazan) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - East of Eden (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Sweet Thursday and musical adaptation, "Pipe Dream" (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - The Short Reign of Pippin IV (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - The Acts of King Arthur and His Noble Knights (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The Winter of Our Discontent (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Journal of a Novel: The East of Eden Letters (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Steinbeck's articles (in Playboy, Esquire, etc.) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Other Steinbeck works (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Adaptations of "Of Mice and Men" (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Adaptations of "Cannery Row" (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - quotes by and about Steinbeck (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Series III: Newspaper Clippings by Date, 1937 - 1984
  - 1937-38 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1940-55 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1957-59 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 1960-67 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 1968-71 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 1972-80 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - 1981-82 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - 1983-84 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - no date (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Series IV: Steinbeck's Personal Occasions and Connections
  - Steinbeck and "the Communists" (Box 1, Folder 31)
    (clippings)
  - 1962 Nobel Prize in Literature (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Steinbeck in Vietnam (Box 1, Folder 33)
    (articles by Steinbeck, clippings)
  - Steinbeck's Death (clippings) (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Commemorative Stamp and Coin (Box 1, Folder 35)
    (clippings, fliers)
  - Steinbeck and Sheffield (Box 1, Folder 36)
    (clippings, article, marriage certificate, etc.)
  - Steinbeck and Covici (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Steinbeck and Stanford (Box 1, Folder 38)
    (clippings and fliers)
- Series V: Biographies of Steinbeck
  - Steinbeck: A Life in Letters by Elaine Steinbeck (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Steinbeck: The Errant Knight by Nelson Valjean (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Friends of John Steinbeck collection of biographical vignettes (Box 1, Folder 41)
    (publicity)
  - In Search of Steinbeck by Anne-Marie Schmitz (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - The Intricate Music by Thomas Kiernan (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - The True Adventures of John Steinbeck by Jonathan Benson (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Series VI: Libraries, Memorials, Foundations, and Centers in memory of Steinbeck
  - Steinbeck Library and Festival (Box 2, Folder 2)
    (fliers, clippings)
  - John Steinbeck Foundation (Box 2, Folder 3)
    (letters, clippings)
  - Steinbeck House and Memorial (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Steinbeck Center Foundation (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - John Steinbeck Society of America (Box 2, Folder 6)
    (newsletters, fliers)
  - Steinbeck Research Center - SJSU (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - California Historical Society (Box 2, Folder 8)
    (newsletters)
- Series VII: Remembering Steinbeck
  - KQED Documentary (Box 2, Folder 9)
    (fliers, clippings, invitation)
  - College courses on Steinbeck - various schools (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Steinbeckiana (Box 2, Folder 11)
    (fliers, pamphlets)
- Series VIII: Related Subjects
  - Steinbeck Country and Cannery Row (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - California Oakies (Box 2, Folder 13)